<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Panta dokimazete a sermon treating of the tryall of all things by the Holy Scriptures, the confest rule of faith and practice  :  shewing the deplorable abuse of that rule, with an attempt touching the examen of ceremonies / delivered in St. Paul's Cathedral November 8, being the xxi Sunday after Trinity, by J.G.</title>
            <author>Goad, J. (John), 1616-1689.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42880</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G902</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R535</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12878596</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12878596</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94901</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42880)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94901)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 380:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Panta dokimazete a sermon treating of the tryall of all things by the Holy Scriptures, the confest rule of faith and practice  :  shewing the deplorable abuse of that rule, with an attempt touching the examen of ceremonies / delivered in St. Paul's Cathedral November 8, being the xxi Sunday after Trinity, by J.G.</title>
                  <author>Goad, J. (John), 1616-1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.R. for Humphrey Robinson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Epistle dedicatory" signed: J. Goad.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94901:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94901:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Παντα Δοχιμαςετε A SERMON Treating of the Tryall of all Things by the HOLY SCRIPTURES, The confeſt Rule of <hi>FAITH</hi> and <hi>PRACTICE,</hi> SHEWING The Deplorable ABUSE of that <hi>Rule;</hi> With an Attempt touching the <hi>Examen</hi> of <hi>CEREMONIES.</hi> Delivered in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Cathedral <hi>November</hi> 8. being the xxi. Sunday after <hi>Trinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <bibl>1 ad <hi>Tim.</hi> v. 8.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <bibl>1 ad <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth.</hi> viii. 2.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>J. G.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. R.</hi> for <hi>Humphrey Robinſon</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Three Pidgeons</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:94901:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur</p>
            <closer>
               <date>Nov. 30. 1663.</date>
               <signed>Tho. Grigg, <hi>Rev. in Chriſto P. D.</hi> Humfr. <hi>Epiſc.</hi> Lond, à <hi>Sacr. Domeſt.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:94901:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Reverend Father in GOD, <hi>Humphry</hi> by Divine Providence Lord Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> our honoured Dioceſan.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat is the ſtate and condition of this Land, and how lamented by ſerious men your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip knows full well. If I appear an unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy means of contributing ſome <hi>Chariſma</hi> toward the ſetling or healing of my Country, I ſhould reach the higheſt of my ambition. Your Lordſhip perceives that all could not be ſaid which was requiſite in the abſtract of an hour. The greateſt argument that ſtaves off ſome good minded people is, the pretence of diſſolute life; which if perfectly true, were an inconſequence, ſeeing 'tis expreſt by our Lord, that the Rabbies which ſay, and do not, as long as they ſit in <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Chair ought to be heard. Howbeit, we hope we can exhibite not a few who ſhall ſet an example to them in all true piety of converſation, provided that affectation of ſanctity and turbulency carry not away the name. My Lord, Either they are Decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers or we; and becauſe 'tis ſo, I thought I could not acquit my ſelf better, then by publiſhing the Churches principles to all the World, whereby She
<pb facs="tcp:94901:3"/>will diſcover, yea and anathematize the contrary Hereſie. All that I have aſſerted is, our Reaſon, our Faith, and our Order, that men may be in ſome way of uſing their Bibles toward Truth and Edification, Spiritual Growth in Duty and Charity, not toward Offences and Diviſions, which by me (by the Grace of God) ſhall not come in to the Church. 'Tis good to have a care of the <hi>Woe through whom</hi>—The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle that bids us hold faſt what is good, in the Text bids us hold faſt our Creed, the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline Apoſtolick <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And this I reckon was not caſual. It is a prodigious thing when the <hi>unlearn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> and <hi>unſtable</hi> cannot endure to hear that the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture may be wreſted, when they are the only men that do it, and that (Lord open their eyes!) to their own damnation. 'Tis a brave thing this ſelf-conceit, being illuminate in our own eyes; true knowledge is ready to puffe up, falſe knowledge puf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feth up more. Let Truth ariſe, and let Error vaniſh from our Cities: Let the unity of the Spirit find a Dwelling amongst us that would be ſpiritual. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the prudent purſuance of which we ſhall pray for the Governors of the Church, and amongſt them for your Lordſhip, as your Lordſhips moſt humbly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. GOAD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94901:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 THESS. V. XXI.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Prove all things: Hold faſt that which is good.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S in the early Spring you cannot but obſerve, walking in a Forreſt, the pleaſant evidences of the ſeaſon, by a Primroſe here, and another there, and not far off a knot crowding toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ſo in the Book of God, you may obſerve here a Leſſon, and there a ſecond, and anon a whole Poſie of flowers (as in this very chapter) grow at your feet, and breath themſelves forth in their ſeveral expirations. But as in this alluſion, it oft times happens there is ſome dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty in gathering, the flower growing perhaps within the empalement of a thorny hedge, or prickly buſh; ſo we do begin to diſcern ſome difficulty alſo, ſome thorn or ſcruple which may threaten us with a raze or a wound, unleſs we are more cautious in gathering.</p>
            <p>The difficulty ariſes from the ſtate of Religion, which ſhould be one unqueſtion'd unmov'd profeſſion; but when we ſee a Nation have ſo loſt themſelves, as in a Forreſt indeed, every one in a ſeveral path, <hi>luring</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps one to another, but not knowing how to come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, nor how to get out: when I ſhall ſee the loweſt members of Chriſts Body learn of <hi>Korah</hi> ſo far, as to take upon them to mutine againſt their Superiours, to define contrary to their Governours, to deviſe Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and to pronounce <hi>Babylon</hi> and <hi>Anathema</hi> to all that diſſent, and theſe men have their eyes as well as others (for, <hi>would we pull out the eyes of theſe men?</hi> ſaid <hi>Korah).</hi> And this ſo far, that our very Civil Peace is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94901:4"/>every hour with deſignes of blood and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; but that our eyes are upon God, who we hope notwithſtanding our provocations (of another nature God knows then what is ſuppoſed) will vouchſafe to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve us.</p>
            <p>When all this which ought to be bemoan'd by every one that underſtands Reaſon or Religion, all this I ſay ſhall be thought to be the genuine Iſſue of the Apoſtles Precept in our Text; and the pretext ſhall be, <hi>What have they done?</hi> but only in Conſcience to God, and love to their own ſouls, <hi>Proved all things;</hi> Proved the Doctrines of the Great Ones, Proved the Government, and Proved all the rabble of their Ceremonies, and they have evidently found the contrary to be <hi>good;</hi> What is left, but that we alſo ſhould <hi>prove</hi> with them, and ſo come over to them or elſe clear up that miſ-underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Apoſtolick exhortation, which hath occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, and will juſtifie this diſ-union.</p>
            <p>And this is our deſigne at this time, through Gods much implored aſſiſtance, to ſhew that theſe words are the Remedy and Antidote rightly underſtood, not any cauſe or occaſion of diſtemper; That if we <hi>prove</hi> and examine all things after the Apoſtles way, we ſhall come to ſettlement and unity, finde the wayes of Truth, and Peace, and Righteouſneſs; we ſhould all light upon this <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Text, and <hi>hold it faſt,</hi> as the Apoſtle exhorts us to do; to which yet he would not exhort us, but that he ſuppoſes it not impoſſible to finde it.</p>
            <p>The words in the verſe will not take up much time for a critical enquiry into their meaning; the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doth indeed here ſignifie what is there rendred, <hi>Prove, i. e.</hi> Try and Examine, and conſequently cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and judge according to their difference; as in that known parallel, 1 <hi>John</hi> IV. 1. <hi>Believe not every ſpirit,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94901:4"/>but try the ſpirits whether they are of God, or no:</hi> Only the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> muſt be reſtrained to a peculiar ſtate of things; Not all things in Philoſophy, or the Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques, the Concluſions, Problems, Experiments; for theſe are exotique to the Chriſtian, though they be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> too in their kind: But <hi>all</hi> that reſpect the <hi>ſpiritual</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, all Doctrines and Principles that belong to Faith and good Manners, that's the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> may be found, the Moral and Spiritual good to be <hi>held faſt,</hi> when found, by Faith and a tenacious obſervance.</p>
            <p>Now ſince all Acts of Examen and Probation are made with reſpect to ſome <hi>Rule;</hi> as in Angles the Square, in Levels the Plumb-line, in Meaſures the Standard; our chief enquiry muſt be, what is this <hi>Rule</hi> according to which our Examen muſt proceed? And ſecondly, Who are the proper Judges to fit on theſe things? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther every one of the Laity, or Clergie only? To whom for certain it only belongs in a <hi>ſpecial</hi> manner, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.2. Upon which account ſome very Learned and Chriſtian men have reſtrain'd the Precept here to <hi>them</hi> only.</p>
            <p>Yet I ſhall not deny them (nor do they I think) their right of Tryal and Judgement, even as far as they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſhall venture, when they ſhall be rightly inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the true nature of application of the Rule on one hand (which is our buſineſs) and conſider ſoberly and meekly the more petite meaſures of their own Parts and Graces; ſeeing God diſpenſeth not his Talents to all equally, but divideth to each man ſeverally as he pleaſeth.</p>
            <p>I ſay, I ſhall not deny them, nor indeed can I, the way I go, provided they uſe the Rule according to the Authors minde, and withal keep themſelves within the bounds that God and Nature hath ſet them, as they will anſwer dearly to God for the contrary, who will
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94901:5"/>have every member to know his own ſtation, as luſty and liking, and thriving as he may be in his own eſteem.</p>
            <p>Howbeit, ſince the Act of Examining and Proving in the Text, ſuppoſing the Rule (with the Spirit of God toward the admiſſion and love of it) is an Act of the Underſtanding, it is clear that the <hi>rational</hi> man is the proper Judge here regarded, the Scripture many times referring things even to <hi>our Judgment,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> x. 15. <hi>Luke</hi> XII. 57. and all the world knows that Judgment is an Act of the Underſtanding.</p>
            <p>For as in the firſt admittance of the Rule we did not take it up upon an eaſie credulity, as the Atheiſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braids us, but upon moſt weighty moment abundantly courting and preſſing us for our aſſent; ſo after that aſſent, the ſame <hi>Reaſon</hi> which draws concluſions for her own uſe, is able to turn and taſte of thoſe which ſhe ſinds drawn to her hand. But in this her Eſtimate of ſo ſacred a thing as Religion, ſhe is not a little jealous and cautious; becauſe a Drug or Jewel the more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious it is, the more do men ſtudy how to adulterate it.</p>
            <p>The Caſe is plain; Religon is not the Fools Goſpel, it deſpiſes not the Fool neither, provided he be a docile, <hi>i.e.</hi> a wiſe Fool. The Body conſiſts not of Babes only, it hath its men, and the Scriptures call upon us to be <hi>men</hi> in underſtanding, that we may approve <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Phil. 1. <hi>the things that are excellent</hi> (for ſo <hi>Heſychius</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains the word); <hi>in all judgment,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that, Pſal. 119. <hi>Teach me good judgment and knowledge</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaith the Hebrew; a ſpiritual taſte to diſtinguiſh, joyn'd in that place with <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which the LXX render by <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>No man ſaies, at leaſt I cannot, that Reaſon can make out the myſteries of Religion, the <hi>Holy Trinity,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94901:5"/>But that Religion hath to do with Reaſon, appears, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no other creature is capable of Religion, and no Law of God can lay hold of us without it: <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill, Thou ſhalt not commit Adultery,</hi> doth not reach us but upon theſe <hi>reaſonable</hi> Suppoſitions; 1. That God ſpeaks to All; 2. That We are ſome of that number.</p>
            <p>For that Reaſon makes inference from the ſacred Text, obſerve the Apoſtle, who having occaſion to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply that place of Scripture to our Lord Chriſt, <hi>[He hath put all things under his feet]</hi> ſteps in and ſayes, that <hi>'Tis Manifest that he is excepted who did put all things under him;</hi> 1 Cor. xv. 27. Manifeſt to what? but to <hi>Reaſon:</hi> as in another place, <hi>'Tis manifeſt that we can carry nothing out of this world;</hi> Manifeſt to <hi>ſenſe</hi> it ſelf.</p>
            <p>But then how our Lord himſelf uſes arguments and deductions from the Text. 'Tis excellent for every one that loves the praxis of Reaſon, to conſider how he handles the Phariſees and Sadducees, and worſts them, as in caſe of the Sabbath; <hi>Do the Prieſts</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>do ſuch butcherly work</hi> as kill and flay the ſacrifice for the ends of God, and may not my Diſciples grinde an ear of corn for the ends of nature? S. <hi>Matth.</hi> xii. 5. May <hi>David</hi>'s Hunger entrench upon the Shew-bread, and muſt we ſtarve in the midſt of a Corn-field? <hi>ver.</hi> 3. and if Circumciſion (when he had heal'd on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath) that <hi>wounding</hi> Ceremony be no violation, a <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> Miracle ſure (ſaith he) is no breach, S. <hi>Joh.</hi> vii. 23.</p>
            <p>Thus in the queſtion of the Souls Immortality, he argues S. <hi>Matth.</hi> xii. 32. If God entitled himſelf to be the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Iſaac,</hi> then ſure they have a perpetual Being and ſubſiſtence with their God; for 'tis no Title of Honour to be the <hi>God of the Dead,</hi> thoſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94901:6"/>that are not the better for him, as They that have no ſubſiſtence are not. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And once more in the caſe of Blaſphemy, <hi>S. Joh.</hi> x. 34. <hi>Jeſus anſwered, Is it not written in your Law, I ſaid you are Gods? If he call them Gods to whom the Word of God came, and the Scripture cannot be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, ſay ye of him,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Nay ſince one way of Probation of all our Hopes, our ever bleſſed Jeſus to be the Meſſias, lies in deduction from the Propheſies of the Old Teſtament, it will be but wrong to intelligent men to ſay any more.</p>
            <p>The reaſonable man then is conſtituted the Judge, after examination and proof to bring in his Inference. What is the Rule now? The Anſwer that is juſtly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected here is the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> the Word of God and of his Prophets, the Law and the Goſpel, the Law of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and the Law of Chriſt. And this Anſwer takes its date from the time in which the Church of God firſt owned the Canon as now it ſtands: For however it pleaſed God to tutour the Patriarchs by Tradition and other Revelations, and to found the Chriſtian Church by the oral Preaching of the Apoſtles, it is evident that ſince he hath committed Both Teſtaments to Writing, ſeeing 'tis his Word, it is our RULE, and being ſuch, no queſtion hath loſt nothing by the writing. All con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing that God had deſignes of ſafety and conſervation of that his Word to the reſpective after-ages, when firſt he began the writing part himſelf.</p>
            <p>I might adde to this, that ONELY Scripture is the Rule, but then I muſt crave leave to diſtinguiſh and take heed that the word <hi>[Onely]</hi> be a juſt excluſive of what is <hi>extraneous</hi> to Scripture, not to have any mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnancy againſt ought that hath <hi>natural intimacy</hi> and conſanguinity with it.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:94901:6"/>
            <p>Of this nature are theſe: (Let notional men diſpute how they differ from Scripture, or from one another:) the conſtant <hi>Belief</hi> of the Church, the conſtant <hi>Publick Practice,</hi> the <hi>Authority</hi> of the Church, the Summaries of Faith, commonly called the <hi>Creed,</hi> the example of Saints of God, the great <hi>example</hi> of our Lord Jeſus, the common <hi>Tradition</hi> and ſenſe of mankind, thoſe notices of good and evill implanted in our ſouls by our great Creator God bleſſed for ever, commonly called <hi>Recta Ratio,</hi> or the light of Nature.</p>
            <p>Some of which are <hi>contain'd</hi> in the Scriptures as the Pith and Marrow of the ſame, as the Creed, and the example of Chriſt, ſome are <hi>ſuppoſed</hi> to the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as right Reaſon, and the light of Nature, and ſome things are <hi>naturally annexed</hi> to the vigor of the Scriptures, <hi>viz.</hi> the authority and practice of the Church in all points which the Scriptures have put into her hand.</p>
            <p>Againſt any of which it will be unjuſt and violent to <hi>oppoſe</hi> the Scriptures upon this account, becauſe they all <hi>agree</hi> in a ſweet and neceſſary ſubordination (at leaſt) one to the other: and 'tis a material rule <hi>ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinata non pugnant</hi> ſubordinates are not to be ſet at va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riance.</p>
            <p>The Scriptures that were left to the Church as a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervatory of Faith, ſince Faith is but One, muſt be left alſo by Gods deſign as a conſervatory of unity. But ſeeing that is loſt among us, it is too apparent, that it is even with the Scriptures, as with other Rules and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments Mathematical, they are exact and infallible in themſelves, but yet every one knows not how to uſe them.</p>
            <p>The error ariſes, becauſe Mathematical Inſtruments are not aſſumed by any, without the precognition of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94901:7"/>ſome <hi>prolepſes</hi> and <hi>postulata</hi> premiſed to their due ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. To give you a more clear example in the <hi>Sun,</hi> which is the <hi>Rule,</hi> the <hi>only Rule</hi> and Index of the hour of the day, ſo certain that all other Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chines muſt be corrected by it: but no man can find that hour of the day by the Sun it ſelf, unleſs he knows before-hand the Horizon, which is Eaſt, and which is Weſt, yea, and the Meridian alſo. Secondly, Theſe Rules muſt be applyed to their proper Correla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives the Ruler for Lines, the Square for Angles; not contrary the Rule for an Angle, or the Square for a Line, they were not given us to that purpoſe. Scripture is a rule according to the Writers intent, of <hi>Faith,</hi> Not of <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> Nor of every dictate of Nature, and <hi>Nature</hi> again is a <hi>rule</hi> of <hi>practice</hi> and conſcience <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in</hi> its ſphere, not of things <hi>beyond</hi> it, matters of meer Faith and myſtery. For want of ſome ſuch directions as theſe I ſay the error ariſes, and doth not the Scripture atteſt the ſame, that men know not how to uſe the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures? Doth not that learned Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſay of ſome that call themſelves Teachers of the Law, <hi>Which yet understand not what they ſay, nor whereof they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently affirm,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.7. Doth not the Scripture con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that the Scripture is and may be <hi>wrested</hi> by ſuch and ſuch perſons, 11 <hi>Pet.</hi> 111.16. Thoſe certainly that know not how to uſe them, Doth it not once again ſay, <hi>That the Law</hi> (the Scripture) <hi>is holy and good;</hi> but then it muſt be uſed <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> lawfully 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.8. to bring us to Chriſt, not to draw us from him, and ſo in like manner to bring us to Unity, not to draw us from it.</p>
            <p>And is not the Scripture then uſed not lawfully, when we wilfully exclude all other Guides, or Lights, or Rules which the Scriptures themſelves own and abet, and impoſe on all that will take her word.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:94901:7"/>
            <p>Theſe things if true (as 'tis pity they ſhould not for Truth, and Peace, and Order ſake) we ſhould quickly learn to ſearch the Wounds of the Church, and tent them, and by Gods grace heal them.</p>
            <p>For all contrary pleas of <hi>ſchiſm</hi> and <hi>diſunion</hi> would fall to the ground, ſince it would be as unreaſonable to ſay, I will be guided by <hi>Scripture</hi> only, not regarding the <hi>Light</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> or common dictates of Conſcience, I will be ſway'd by <hi>Scripture</hi> only, not reſpecting any <hi>Creeds</hi> or ſummaries of Faith, how antient ſoever, I will be judged by <hi>Scripture</hi> only, defying all manner of <hi>publick Teſtimony</hi> or <hi>Tradition,</hi> whether it hath footing in the Scripture or no: <hi>Scripture</hi> ſhall be my <hi>Rule,</hi> not the <hi>example</hi> of Chriſt (for many cry up the one, that little think they are obliged to the other) This upon deliberation will appear to be q.d. I will be guided by the <hi>Sun</hi> alone, not by the imaginary <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>West,</hi> or the humane invention of the <hi>Meridian:</hi> I will build my Houſe level by the Plumb-line, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding which is up, and which is down.</p>
            <p>Now ſince we are engaged to prove <hi>all</hi> things matters of <hi>Faith, Practice,</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> alſo, you are to take notice, (that we may <hi>duely</hi> prove all things) that there is a difference between the former and latter: that the difference ſtands thus, as I truſt we ſhall make it good; that the Scripture which is a <hi>distinct Rule</hi> for Faith and Practice; is <hi>not ſuch</hi> for matters of <hi>Diſcipline.</hi> It is only <hi>general</hi> for this; as <hi>viz.</hi> When it commands Decency, and Order, and Obedience, but in <hi>particular</hi> it is not; whence a diſtinct teſtimony of <hi>Scripture</hi> is not to be called for by our <hi>Poſers</hi> for every Eccleſiaſtical Uſage, nay it is ignorant and abſurd ſo to think: but in the other a <hi>distinct Rule</hi> is indeed acknowledged. Yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain with theſe cautions, that in matters of Faith no
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94901:8"/>interpretation of Scripture muſt thwart the <hi>Creed,</hi> or in matters of <hi>Practice</hi> croſs-grain the <hi>Light of Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To begin with this firſt. The <hi>Light of Nature</hi> and <hi>Natural</hi> Principles are <hi>ſuppoſed</hi> to the holy Scriptures, as Unit is to Numbers, or the Dawning of the day to the Sun-riſe, a Beam of the Divine Conſcience ſhot into the ſoul in the day of the Creation, when God ſaid to the little World, <hi>Let there be light, and there was light,</hi> and God ſaw that it was good. And though great was the loſs of that light in our firſt Father, yet the growing darkneſs reach'd not ſo far (without queſtion) as to extinguiſh <hi>all</hi> that was good; the very <hi>ſhame</hi> that was left him was a ſign of <hi>ſome</hi> good remains: he knew that diſobedience was nakedneſs, his fear and flying for the ſame ſhew that he was not paſt all grace, he was not delivered up <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> No Divine ever ſaid ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Natural Principles</hi> therefore remain in us; and if they ſhould not, without doubt we ſhould all run like Beaſts into the Wilderneſs, with <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> in the head of us: for by theſe all mankind know, (ſince I queſtion whether the Sea-Monſters in our ſhape be of the ſame race with us) <hi>know,</hi> I ſay, <hi>Good and Evil,</hi> that there is a GOD, a Law, a Vengeance, a Worſhip, and we give more then gueſſes at what is truly <hi>Honeſt,</hi> and <hi>Iuſt,</hi> and <hi>Modeſt,</hi> what <hi>becomes</hi> our natures, and what miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becomes us <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt, Inhumane,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nholy</hi> alſo.</p>
            <p>For the Heathen always could, and can to this day tell us, what is the iniquity of <hi>Perjury</hi> and <hi>Parricide,</hi> Sacriledge and Fraud, the iniquity of unhallowing ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Rites and Times by ſervile Work, or by impure Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes.</p>
            <p>Hence the Apoſtle tells us, that all the works of the fleſh are <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>manifeſt,</hi> Gal. v. to the rational Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. 'Tis true, it muſt be enlightned by faith to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94901:8"/>know <hi>Idolatry, Witchcraft,</hi> or <hi>Hereſie</hi> (at leaſt) to be works of darkneſs, but for the reſt they are all <hi>manifeſt</hi> to meer Reaſon, Adultery, Fornication, Strife, Sedition, Hatred, Envyings, Murthers, Drunkenneſs, and ſuch like.</p>
            <p>Adde that great known place, <hi>Rom.</hi> ii. 14, 15. <hi>The Gentiles do by nature the things contained in the Law,</hi> and <hi>Having not the Law, they are a Law unto themſelves.</hi> Having not the Books of <hi>Moſes,</hi> they are a <hi>Moſes</hi> to themſelves, becauſe many of them made conſcience of theſe ſinful works of the fleſh now reckoned up.</p>
            <p>To ſpeak plain then, This <hi>Law of Nature</hi> is a <hi>Rule,</hi> no prejudice to <hi>Scripture:</hi> For if it ſhall be asked, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be <hi>ſin</hi> to tranſgreſs it? who ſees not that the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer muſt be, yea: that all <hi>unnatural</hi> men are <hi>impious,</hi> which is a perfect demonſtration, that this <hi>Law</hi> is a <hi>Rule,</hi> becauſe as we may ſin againſt the Scripture, ſo we may ſin againſt it. Nay who knows not that it is an aggravation of ſin, the more groſſely and palpably it affronts this <hi>innate</hi> light, ſuch as the <hi>unnatural</hi> luſts, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. the unnatural burning of their children to that curſed Idol <hi>Moloch,</hi> and the like.</p>
            <p>Upon which it is evident, that the Word of God cannot, according to Gods intent, be univerſally <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed</hi> to this Law, becauſe <hi>this</hi> is alſo Gods, <hi>Gods</hi> own <hi>Law,</hi> written in the Table of our hearts, as the other (if yet it be the other) was in Tables of Stone. I may well ſay, if yet <hi>it be</hi> the other: For all Divines that I know confeſs, that the <hi>Ten Commandments</hi> for the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral part are all <hi>one</hi> with the Primaeval <hi>Law of Nature.</hi> Now there is no oppoſing of God to God, Redemption to Creation, Grace to Nature, the one is <hi>more excellent</hi> then the other, but they are at no hand <hi>oppoſite,</hi> one does not overthrow the other.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:94901:9"/>
            <p>Here if it be asked, Whether all <hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions</hi> rational are compris'd in <hi>Scripture,</hi> (a material Quere toward the underſtanding of our Texts buſineſs) the anſwer (for the <hi>concluſions</hi>) muſt be Negative. The Scriptures do charge many of them upon us with this dreadful caution, <hi>Ego Dominus, Thou ſhalt not curſe the Deaf, I am the Lord; or put a ſtumbling-block before the Blind, I am the Lord:</hi> yet the <hi>concluſions</hi> drawn from Natural light are <hi>Infinite,</hi> as Chriſts Miracles, which Saint <hi>John</hi> ſaith the Scriptures could not hold. Be judge your ſelves, when every true and wholeſome Leſſon in <hi>Practick Philoſophy,</hi> yea all the <hi>grave</hi> and <hi>righteous</hi> Laws of <hi>Policies</hi> and Nations are nought elſe but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions from the <hi>Law of Nature:</hi> and who can under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to find then <hi>distinctly</hi> in the holy Scriptures, <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly,</hi> I ſay; for in the <hi>general</hi> 'tis true they may be found, eſpecially above other places in that famous Text of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to his <hi>Philippians,</hi> chap. iv. 8. where he conjures them to whatſoever things are <hi>true,</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever things are <hi>grave,</hi> whatſoever things are <hi>pure, juſt, lovely,</hi> and of <hi>good report,</hi> if <hi>there be any vertue</hi> or <hi>peace,</hi> to think on them.</p>
            <p>But <hi>distinctly</hi> and <hi>expreſly</hi> to ſind every wholſome Law of this <hi>Land</hi> in the Law or Goſpel, I appeal to the knowing in the Law, if they will ſay it; it is enough, that they are not <hi>contrary,</hi> and 'tis a ſign there is <hi>God</hi> in them, becauſe not <hi>contrary</hi> to Scripture, according to our principle above. And</p>
            <p>It is pity but Chriſtians ſhould underſtand theſe things, as long as they are the words of Truth and Soberneſs. The holy <hi>Scripture</hi> is careful to teach us to do our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to <hi>God,</hi> to pray, to <hi>hope</hi> on him; but it is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſollicitous to teach us in what <hi>common ſenſe</hi> can ſufficiently tutour us. I inſtance in one of many, <hi>viz.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94901:9"/>Conſulting the Phyſician,</hi> or uſing any <hi>good means</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward our recovery. The Son of <hi>Sirach</hi> indeed minds us of it, but he is <hi>Apocryphal,</hi> and the <hi>Canonical</hi> in the caſe of <hi>Aſa</hi> ſeems to condemn it: and ſo for the uſe of all natural <hi>means</hi> in general. 'Tis ridiculous to preſs me for a Text of Scripture, if <hi>Right Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Humanity</hi> ſufficiently inſtructs us: For Reaſon is a <hi>Talent</hi> alſo, of which God will take his account.</p>
            <p>Hence the <hi>Libertines</hi> muſt learn their no Plea for Fornication, and Drunkenneſs, and Gluttony, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling, and ſelf-Murthers, nor Pride and Haughtineſs, although poſſibly they are not expreſt in the Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue. Nor muſt men venture in the Topick of Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony on <hi>Poligamy,</hi> Marriage of Kin, Matches precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate or unequal, or haſty ſecond Matching within the dayes of mourning for the firſt, although they fancy no <hi>Text</hi> that condemns them. The like may be ſaid for <hi>Sacriledge</hi> (which ſure many think no <hi>Text</hi> forbids the Chriſtian) breaking open of Graves, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yea all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modeſt offenſive <hi>Cynical</hi> behaviour to civil Company, remembring that they are condemned in the <hi>general, Charity behaveth not it ſelf unſeemly,</hi> 1 Cor. xiii. and <hi>Provide things honeſt in the ſight of all men,</hi> Rom. xii. 17. And if in the <hi>ſpecial</hi> they are not found, let them take notice that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> hath an <hi>Et caetera</hi> for them, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>and ſuch like;</hi> a place to be ſtudied by all conſciencious perſons, <hi>Gal.</hi> v. 21.</p>
            <p>All that the <hi>Light of Nature</hi> teaches muſt be <hi>ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> and <hi>granted</hi> beforehand by him that means to read the <hi>Scriptures.</hi> What ſaith the Apoſtle in the caſe of Ruffian hair, <hi>Doth not even nature it ſelf teach you,</hi> ſaith he, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> xi. 14. q.d. Suppoſe the <hi>Scripture</hi> be <hi>ſilent,</hi> doth not <hi>that</hi> ſufficiently teach us.</p>
            <p>Let Interpreters be conſulted on thoſe words, with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94901:10"/>thoſe of <hi>Rom.</hi> xiv. ult. <hi>Whatſoever is not of faith, is ſin,</hi> and the more knowing will be ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>To put all out of doubt, when our Saviour was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of <hi>breaking</hi> a Text, does he not retreat to ſound <hi>Reaſon,</hi> thereby ſhewing us, that <hi>Scripture</hi> muſt ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or never (excepting in the <hi>mysterious</hi> parts, as we ſaid above) be conſtrain'd <hi>againſt</hi> it. I have heal'd one on the Sabbath day, 'tis true, and you condemn me, but without <hi>reaſon:</hi> ſo <hi>Which of you having an Oxe or an Aſs fallen into a pit, will not ſtraightway help it out on the Sabbath day,</hi> S. Luke xiv. 5. and again, <hi>Is it lawful to do good, or to do evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I deſire that our Saviour may be obſerved, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when he ſaith, <hi>He came not to destroy the Law;</hi> he doth not mean the <hi>Moral</hi> and <hi>Natural</hi> Law alſo. I am ſure that place of <hi>Hoſea, I will have mercy and not ſacrifice.</hi> Whatever <hi>Hoſea</hi> meant, he applyes it to <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> to ones <hi>ſelf</hi> in the caſe of the <hi>ſhew-bread,</hi> S. Mat. xii. 7. Secondly, I deſire it be obſerved, whether our Saviour throwes not the name of <hi>Hypocrite</hi> on thoſe pretences mainly, which may be proved to be <hi>not ſincere</hi> by the ſtrength of <hi>Reaſon;</hi> as to deny <hi>Tribute</hi> to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and yet ſee the <hi>ſuperſcription,</hi> to wipe the <hi>outſide,</hi> and let the <hi>inſide</hi> be filthy, to behold the <hi>mote</hi> in my brothers eye, and not conſider the <hi>beam</hi> in my own eye, to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered in the preſence of my <hi>Master,</hi> and not to ſhew the ſame reverence in the preſence of my <hi>God.</hi> I could adde more, but I ſhall be too long on this point; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this muſt not be omitted: That <hi>Religion</hi> without <hi>Reaſon</hi> may carry us into a <hi>Frenzy.</hi> I would this Land of ours did not ſhew you the truth of what I deliver. The Spirit of God is no <hi>frantick</hi> Spirit, but the Spirit of love and a ſound mind, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> i. 7. The <hi>Apostle</hi> asks his diſorderly <hi>Corinthians</hi> what they mean, <hi>Will not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94901:10"/>they ſay that you are mad,</hi> 1 Cor. xiv. 21. The Apoſtle would not have us be of a <hi>crackt</hi> Religion.</p>
            <p>If then the <hi>Light of Nature</hi> implanted in us be ſuch a Light, which we muſt have recourſe to when the caſe ſerves, if that muſt alſo with the holy <hi>Scriptures</hi> have ſome ſhare in <hi>proving</hi> all things, then we are ſomething toward a ſettlement, we have what will keep us <hi>ſober</hi> at leaſt, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Rom.</hi> xii. 3. We ſhall put up no hideous impudent pretences that ſhall dare to thwart this Light; we ſhall not be wild or brutiſh with the untamed Heifers, or the wild Aſs that ſnuffes in the Wilderneſs; we ſhall not be like the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous Fiſh of the Sea that have no Ruler; we ſhall not preach down <hi>Crowns</hi> and <hi>Scepters,</hi> the Ordinance of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi> and ſet that new Magiſtrate the <hi>People</hi> above them. On pretence of <hi>Freedom</hi> we ſhall not bring in <hi>Confuſion,</hi> and invade other mens Eſtates on the Plea of <hi>Saintſhip;</hi> we ſhall not from the example of <hi>Jael, Phineas,</hi> and the <hi>Canaanite</hi> preach hideous <hi>Maſſacres</hi> of all the <hi>Loyal Party,</hi> to ſuch numerous Congregations which are able to do the feat; we ſhall not with thoſe <hi>Fanaticks</hi> in <hi>Jeremy</hi> vii. 10. believe that we can poſſibly be <hi>redeemed even to commit ſuch abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations;</hi> we ſhall have none ſtrip themſelves of Shame and Garments, and diſplay themſelves <hi>Naked</hi> through our once civil Streets; none will deſie the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilities of a <hi>ſalute:</hi> we ſhall not ſtudy to do things quite contrary to <hi>humanity,</hi> only becauſe all mankind that were in their wits had done ſo before; we ſhall not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get we are <hi>men,</hi> becauſe we are <hi>fellow creatures;</hi> we ſhall ſave our <hi>natures,</hi> if we do not ſave our <hi>ſouls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo much for the firſt particular, <hi>Prove all things,</hi> which concern <hi>Conſcience</hi> by the <hi>Rule</hi> of holy <hi>Scripture,</hi> but <hi>at no hand excluding</hi> the <hi>Light</hi> of Reaſon or <hi>Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:94901:11"/>
            <p>Our ſecond particular treats of the <hi>proof</hi> in matters of <hi>Faith,</hi> Faith ſtrictly ſo called: in which ſenſe not every point of Spiritual Knowledge is an Article of Faith, <hi>i. e.</hi> neceſſary to ſalvation: the Scriptures are the <hi>Rule</hi> of both Faith and Spiritual Knowledge, but ſo as their interpretation keep a fair correſpondence with the <hi>Rule</hi> of Faith, the <hi>Creed,</hi> the publick confeſſion of Chriſt from the firſt minute of Chriſtianity, made in the Church by all the Candidates of the holy <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> as you hear by the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the firſt Perſon, <hi>I believe,</hi> &amp;c. Which confeſſion is brought down to after Ages; not in Tables of Stone, ſaith Saint <hi>Hierome,</hi> but <hi>in the hearts of them that believe unto righteouſneſs, and in the mouths of thoſe that have made confeſſion to ſalvation:</hi> For to this very practice doth the <hi>Apostle</hi> there referre, <hi>Rom.</hi> x.</p>
            <p>The greateſt ſearchers into the annals of the Church <hi>Voſſ. de Symb.</hi> confeſs, that the Apoſtles Creed, as now it ſtands, was in uſe above twelve hundred years ago, <hi>viz.</hi> before four hundred years after Chriſt. Let us take their grant, and let us ask them in the Name of Chriſt; Was the <hi>Apostles Creed</hi> then thought an <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation:</hi> ſuch inferences giddy people are apt to make. But if we look into the Scriptures, there we ſhall find that <hi>Catechiſm</hi> into the Faith of Chriſt, and <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of the ſame is elder then the very name of <hi>Christian, Acts</hi> xi.26. as it muſt be, becauſe nothing elſe could give them that name, Elder by ſome years then the writings of the New Teſtament. Saint <hi>Lukes Theophilus</hi> was catechis'd into Chriſtian Religion, before the <hi>Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt</hi> wrote his <hi>Goſpel,</hi> S. Luke i.4.</p>
            <p>The Creed and the ſumme of Chriſtianity differ <hi>ſecundum magis &amp; minus,</hi> a ſtraiter and a larger com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, the <hi>Creed</hi> believes the Son of God, the ſumme
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94901:11"/>of Chriſtianity ſaith <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>of one ſubstance</hi> with the Father. This believes the Reſurrection of the <hi>Body,</hi> that explaines it ſelf a Shining and <hi>Glorious Body;</hi> they differ not in <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> but as the Bud and the <hi>Roſe</hi> in <hi>Explication</hi> only.</p>
            <p>Now the ſumme of Chriſtianity is the <hi>Immediate Rule</hi> of Faith, the Scriptures being the <hi>Rule</hi> quatenus They contain in them this great Pawn and Pledg, the grand <hi>Depoſitum</hi> of our Religion. This <hi>Depoſitum</hi> was left with the Church, and alſo committed to writing. Left with the Church; thence the Apoſtle exhorts in in ſeveral places to hold it faſt. So 2 Tim. i.13. <hi>Hold faſt the Form of ſound words in Faith and Love which is in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Obſerve firſt, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>Form</hi> of ſound words, a <hi>Draught,</hi> a <hi>Breviate,</hi> (ſo <hi>Ptolomy</hi> calls his <hi>Maps</hi> of the World <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) a <hi>Form</hi> and a <hi>Rule;</hi> Thus is our <hi>LORD</hi>'s <hi>Prayer</hi> a <hi>Form</hi> of ſound words, and a <hi>Rule</hi> (viz.) of Prayer; the <hi>Decalogue</hi> a <hi>Form</hi> of ſound words, and a <hi>Rule</hi> of Life. Obſerve 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> a Form of <hi>ſound words,</hi> or rather <hi>ſound Articles</hi> and Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for <hi>ſingle words</hi> are not capable of <hi>ſoundneſs</hi> or of the <hi>contrary.</hi> Thirdly, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of this Form, the <hi>Credenda</hi> and <hi>Agenda,</hi> as all Creeds rightly underſtood do contain Matters of <hi>Faith</hi> and Matters of <hi>Practiſe,</hi> witneſs that <hi>Article</hi> of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion</hi> of ſins <hi>Gloriouſly</hi> and <hi>Catholickly</hi> explained by, <hi>I believe one Baptiſme to Remiſſion of ſins.</hi> Now theſe <hi>Credenda</hi> and <hi>Agenda</hi> the Apoſtle calls <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> which is in Chriſt Jeſus. Next, that this Form muſt be <hi>held faſt,</hi> that's ſome ſigne it was of no unreaſonable extent; it muſt be graſſed firſt before it can be held faſt: ſuch as doth not overlade the <hi>Memorie,</hi> as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſeems to ſpeak, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> xv.2. where he is explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94901:12"/>the <hi>Articles</hi> of the Creed: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Conſtrue it how you pleaſe, it makes for us.</p>
            <p>Now to tell us that at firſt,<note place="margin">Voſſ, de 36. Symb. dep. 3. p. 14</note> it was enough for the Baptized to profeſs <hi>Belief in the Lord Jeſus,</hi> or the <hi>Name of the Father, Son,</hi> and <hi>Holy Ghoſt, Act.</hi> ii. ch. viii. 12, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is contrary to thoſe very <hi>Scriptures</hi> and <hi>Reaſon.</hi> For he that believeth in the Lord Jeſus, doth not believe in thoſe <hi>two words</hi> only, but in all thoſe <hi>Great Things</hi> concerning him; All that he hath any way done and ſaid to the Redemption of the world, his immaculate <hi>Conception,</hi> his <hi>Paſſion, Reſurrection, Miſſion</hi> of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and, the end of all, the bleſſed <hi>Remiſsion of our ſins.</hi> And thus we have a Little <hi>Creed</hi> at leaſt.</p>
            <p>And 'tis evident that the very <hi>Inſtitution</hi> of Chriſt points at a larger Form, when he hath appointed all <hi>Baptized</hi> Perſons to profeſs Belief in the <hi>Father, Son,</hi> and <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> S. <hi>Matth.</hi> xxviii. Belief in their <hi>Names</hi> too, which in the Firſt Perſon cannot ſignifie leſs then God the Father Almighty, Creator of the World, and that's all the <hi>Apostles Creed</hi> expreſſes; and the Third Perſon the Holy Ghoſt cannot imply leſs then the Lord and Giver of Spiritual Life, as the <hi>Nicene Creed</hi> hath it, which yet the <hi>Apoſtles Creed</hi> ſpares to expreſs.</p>
            <p>It muſt not be denied but that the <hi>Antient</hi> Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Church of God in ſeveral places did not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to every <hi>title</hi> or ſyllable: the <hi>East</hi> and <hi>Western</hi> Church had ſeveral Forms, as to this matter; nay, that of <hi>Aquileia</hi> in the ſame <hi>Italy</hi> differ'd ſaith <hi>Ruffinus</hi> from that at <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let it be conſidered that there was no <hi>Confeſsion</hi> recited in publick but was in order <hi>to Baptiſme,</hi> yea and what preſuppoſed a <hi>Larger Catechiſme</hi> of the Novice in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Myſteries and Duties of Religion; and then where
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94901:12"/>will be the variety, or will it not be fupplied out of the Principles premiſed to a perfect Agreement?</p>
            <p>To illuſtrate this, bating the <hi>Deſcent</hi> into Hell, as the <hi>Romane Creed</hi> did, and the <hi>Communion</hi> of Saints with <hi>Aquileia,</hi> of which we cannot diſcourſe here what is there in the <hi>Creed,</hi> but is witneſſed to have been there, and <hi>naturally must</hi> be from the beginning?</p>
            <p>For could any Confeſſion leave out the Article of <hi>Remiſsion</hi> of ſin? What, and be a Confeſſion in order to <hi>Baptiſme?</hi> Did any omit the Article of the <hi>Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection?</hi> Nay. 'Tis confeſt none did, and good reaſon too; for without this Article our Religion were a <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> xv.14. or the Incarnation of Jeſus, or his Death, or coming to Judgment, could any Confeſſion or Catechiſme leave theſe out?</p>
            <p>Nay further, Is it not <hi>natural</hi> for a new Convert in the day of his Addition to the <hi>Church,</hi> to profeſs <hi>Sancta Eccleſia,</hi> the <hi>Holy Church</hi> that was then deſcending into the Laver of Baptiſm the Sacrament of <hi>Initiation</hi> into that <hi>Church,</hi> therefore <hi>Holy,</hi> becauſe none but the waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and the ſanctified did enter? Or was the word <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique</hi> Church a new Addition (as is pretended) to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the prevention of <hi>Horeſie?</hi> this is but ſuſpected by thoſe that it may be conſider not the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in S. <hi>Peters</hi> and S. <hi>James</hi>'s Epiſtles: But as to the thing, it is evident they believed in the <hi>Apostolique,</hi> and what is <hi>Apostolique throughout the World,</hi> but <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What then if the <hi>Apostles Creed,</hi> as it is call'd, were not a <hi>Form</hi> agreed by them <hi>totidem ſyllabis;</hi> yet the <hi>Effect</hi> and ſubſtance was agreed among them before e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they departed from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to go preach to every Creature? Do not the Church Monuments tell us ſo
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94901:13"/>much? See <hi>Ruffinus in Symbol.</hi> S. <hi>Ambroſ. ep.</hi> 81. <hi>Hieron. ep. ad Pamach.</hi> quoted by <hi>Voſsius diſp.</hi> 1. <hi>ſect.</hi> 13. Nay you that will take the paines of a Pilgrimage to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> may be ſhewn the very place where the <hi>Fame</hi> ſays they made this Agreement. See Mr <hi>Sandys</hi> and Mr <hi>Moriſons</hi> Relations.</p>
            <p>But why trifle we? Did the Apoſtles trow ye preach <hi>Chriſt</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi> And what is preaching of <hi>Chriſt</hi> but preaching <hi>ſuch Articles</hi> concerning him, his <hi>Dying</hi> for our ſins, <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> and <hi>Repentance</hi> unto Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>ſins?</hi> Muſt we prove this out of <hi>Scripture?</hi> Nothing more eaſie. See <hi>Act.</hi> viii.5. <hi>cum</hi> 12. xxviii.31. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> i.23. xv.12. <hi>Eph.</hi> vv.19, 20. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> iii.2. <hi>Gal.</hi> iii.1. Did not they then going abroad preach the <hi>ſame Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>ſame Goſpel,</hi> i. the ſame <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and Bodie of Articles? How is it called <hi>Eph.</hi> xv.5. <hi>One Faith, indiviſa in ſe &amp; diviſa à quolibet alio?</hi> What is meant by the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitie of that ſpirit</hi> which preacht Chriſt farr and near? <hi>Eph.</hi> iv.3. And how is heed taken leaſt they ſhould preach 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> xi.4. <hi>ſeveral Jeſuses,</hi> any Form of Doctrine that ſhould be diſſonant from the Truth, as a <hi>falſe</hi> ſcheme of the Grace of God? Hence that of 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> v.12. the <hi>true Grace of God wherein ye ſtand?</hi> Did they preach the <hi>Name</hi> of Chriſt &amp; not the <hi>Thing?</hi> Did they preach him any how? or only did they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt but <hi>One</hi> ſaving way, <hi>as the Truth is in Jeſus,</hi> Eph. iv.21. not introducing any <hi>falſe Article,</hi> for then 'tis a danger <hi>Chriſt may profit nothing,</hi> Gal. v.2. Nor omitting any true one, eſpecially that Great Article of <hi>RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PENTANCE</hi> involved in Remiſhon of ſins; for the Apoſtle hopes, whatever ſome may teach, that His Charge will not <hi>learn Christ</hi> SO: ſo falſely, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Eph. iv.19. What need we look for further preſumtions,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94901:13"/>when as Chriſts Inſtitution is extant to his Apoſtles, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to teach all Nations, and to <hi>Baptize</hi> them (Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chize them firſt) into the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt. This only is enough to evidence it.</p>
            <p>What is the iſſue then? The ſumme of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is a <hi>Rule,</hi> then is the <hi>Creed</hi> alſo a <hi>Rule</hi> of Faith. The firſt appears from ſeveral places of the Scripture,—<hi>You have obeyed from the heart</hi> that <hi>Form of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> Rom. vi.17. <hi>That Form</hi> is the <hi>Rule</hi> of their Faith and Obedience. A <hi>Rule</hi> I ſay of Faith; for if any man ſhall teach <hi>contrary to it,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, tranſgreſs that <hi>Rule,</hi> he muſt be <hi>marked</hi> for one that cauſes <hi>Diviſions</hi> and <hi>Herefies</hi> in the Church, <hi>Rom.</hi> xvi.17. Yea, if an Angel from heaven ſhal dare to do it, he ſhall have his <hi>anathema</hi> as the Hereticks have, <hi>Gal.</hi> i. Hence 'tis expreſly called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the Rule,</hi> as I could make it out, <hi>Gal.</hi> vi.16.</p>
            <p>The ſecond appears from the illuſtrious Teſtimony of the <hi>Primitive</hi> uncorrupted Church, in which ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly and deliberately the <hi>Creed</hi> is noted as<note n="(a)" place="margin">Tertul. de Trin.</note> 
               <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gula Fidei,</hi> there being no other ſumme of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty extant but that. And that you may ſee <hi>Tertullian</hi> lookt upon it as <hi>the Rule,</hi> you ſhall finde him<note n="(b)" place="margin">adverſ. Marcion, l. 4.</note> 
               <hi>trying</hi> the Spirits, and the Doctrines, and the falſe Prophets, yea and their falſe Goſpels too by it. To this purpoſe he formally repeats it to the Heretick as <hi>univerſally</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted from the beginning. <hi>Marcion</hi> forſooth did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve a ſeveral God in the Old Teſtament and in the New, and had a falſe Goſpel coyn'd under the name of S. <hi>Luke.</hi> This Antient Writer<note n="(c)" place="margin">Prax. contr. P. &amp; de Virg. ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note> repels both, becauſe the Creed began <hi>I believe in One God,</hi> &amp;c. And this was within leſſe then<note n="(d)" place="margin">ab ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelii decu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curriſſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. Prax.</note> 100 years after S. <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſt.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:94901:14"/>
            <p>And had not Saint <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſt taught him and us this very Method of Examen? who is he that bids us not <hi>believe every Spirit,</hi> but <hi>try the Spirits,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they are of God or no, 1 <hi>John</hi> iv.1. Now how muſt that be done? even by the <hi>Articles of our Creed,</hi> by the <hi>Rules</hi> of the Catholick Faith, ſay the Contents of that Chapter. You ſhall hear him. <hi>Hereby know ye the Spirit of God:</hi> That's good; How? <hi>Every Spirit that confeſſeth that Ieſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh, is of God,</hi> verſ. 2. <hi>and every Spirit that confeſſeth not, is not of God.</hi> He gives his <hi>Criterium</hi> from an <hi>Article</hi> of the Creed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Hereticks of that Time which oppugned it; for ſo the words following import, <hi>This is that Spirit of Antichriſt,</hi> verſ. 3. <hi>that even now already is in the World.</hi> He doth not, 'tis true, give <hi>One Catholick Rule</hi> to try <hi>all Hereſies</hi> by; for how many <hi>Hereticks</hi> were there, that were ſo cunning afterward, as to confeſs the Incarnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> obſerves on that place: but he giveth one <hi>pro tempore,</hi> ſufficient at that time, and from the Creed he fetcheth it.</p>
            <p>But the holy Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks of <hi>all</hi> the <hi>Creed:</hi> For when he had ſeaſonably admoniſh'd us, that ſome do abuſe and <hi>wreſt</hi> the holy Scriptures, he gives us an account <hi>who they</hi> are, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>unlearned,</hi> and the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable;</hi> which can be none elſe but thoſe that have not ſufficiently <hi>learned,</hi> and are not ſtrongly <hi>confirmed</hi> in the <hi>fundamental</hi> Leſſons of Chriſtianity, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> iii.16.</p>
            <p>The Scripture then is the <hi>un-erring Rule</hi> of Faith, but ſo that its interpretation muſt have regard to the Rule and <hi>ſymbole</hi> of our Faith: the reaſons are the ſame as before, becauſe they ſweetly <hi>agree;</hi> the one is <hi>contai'nd</hi> in the other, the one is <hi>ſuppos'd</hi> by the other, as we ſaid of the <hi>Law of Nature.</hi> They are mutual helps
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94901:14"/>one to the other. The <hi>Scriptures</hi> were given, that our Faith might not be <hi>interlop'd,</hi> and the <hi>Creed</hi> was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven that the Scripture might not <hi>be wrested,</hi> Neither can be ſpared by the faithful.</p>
            <p>So here's no claſhing; the <hi>Decalogue</hi> is <hi>the Rule,</hi> but not to ſhut out the <hi>Pentateuch.</hi> The five Books of <hi>Moſes</hi> are the <hi>Rule,</hi> but not to exclude <hi>the Ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> Nothing muſt exclude its own <hi>Quinteſſence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And is not this neceſſary? No queſtion God ſaw it very neceſſary; and the advantages are undeniably theſe: Firſt, The Creed is one <hi>compact abridgement</hi> of fundamentals, which in the Scripture lie as in the Myne here and there reſperſed. Secondly, It is <hi>plain and eaſie;</hi> but the Scriptures have <hi>many things hard to be understood:</hi> So ſaid Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> when yet the Book of the <hi>Revelation</hi> was not written. Hence the old He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks few or none denied the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> but the <hi>Creed</hi> many diſowned.</p>
            <p>After all this are we not nearer to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> now? Yes: For if this <hi>Rule</hi> were believed to be a <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Form</hi> preſerved to us <hi>from the beginning,</hi> we ſhould none of us dream of <hi>new Lights,</hi> and ſtand amazed at every <hi>puffe</hi> of doctrine from this, or that, or the other <hi>illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſhould not reckon ſalvation by any <hi>Name</hi> but <hi>Jeſus,</hi> nor by that neither unleſs rightly underſtood.</p>
            <p>We ſhould not <hi>divide</hi> Chriſt into Pariſhes, piece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meal, making ſo many <hi>Catechiſms</hi> as <hi>Congregations,</hi> and <hi>Christianities</hi> as <hi>Pulpits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſhould none of us dare to ſcruple the very God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of our Bleſſed Lord and the Worlds <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> founded in it; we ſhould not out-face the Church of God in her <hi>main</hi> myſterie; whereby ſhe is diſtinguiſhed from
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94901:15"/>the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Synagogue, or the Turkiſh <hi>Moſque.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſhould not dare to <hi>contract</hi> this great ſalvation, and deny the <hi>univerſality</hi> of Chriſts merits.</p>
            <p>We ſhall not abuſe the grace of God, either to <hi>preſume</hi> on a profane, or to be <hi>ſecure</hi> in an indifferent life.</p>
            <p>We ſhould regard and reſpect the <hi>known</hi> wayes of Chriſt, <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> &amp;c. not dreaming of an inviſible Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to twitch us to Heaven by the hair of the head.</p>
            <p>There is none of us would make it an <hi>Article,</hi> much leſs place <hi>all</hi> our <hi>ſaving Faith</hi> in an infallible abſolute <hi>aſſurance</hi> of our well-doing. We ſhould rather <hi>tremble</hi> at the brightneſs of Him that is to come judge Quick and Dead, and <hi>tremble</hi> again at our ſacrilegious breaches of our <hi>Vow</hi> in Baptiſm, and our indevout repentances therefore.</p>
            <p>We ſhould not imagine no neceſſity of <hi>holineſs</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward eternal remiſſion of ſins, we ſhould not be afraid of <hi>good Works,</hi> Thing, nor Name.</p>
            <p>We ſhould talk <hi>leſs</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and live <hi>more</hi> by it. We ſhould look upon Chriſtianity as a kind of pure <hi>Angelical</hi> life, the <hi>exertion</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in <hi>Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſhould believe a <hi>Church,</hi> be ſuch <hi>men</hi> in under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding as to <hi>know</hi> our <hi>Mother,</hi> and ſo <hi>natural</hi> as to <hi>reverence</hi> her.</p>
            <p>We ſhould not make ſuch a vaſt <hi>Hiatns</hi> in Church-Hiſtory, as to reckon none from the <hi>Apostles</hi> to our dayes: for if we reckon <hi>any,</hi> we could not place <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> in a <hi>wilful departure</hi> from it in every thing where <hi>humour</hi> prompts us to do that eaſie thing of <hi>wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And (to ſee that I would be impartial) neither
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94901:15"/>ſhould we out of a pretended eſteem of this Apoſtolick <hi>Form,</hi> content our ſelves with a ſcanty meaſure of the <hi>knowledge</hi> of Chriſt: Seeing there is Duty and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and to <hi>believe in Chriſt</hi> rightly underſtood is a World of both. And thus much for proving of matters of Faith.</p>
            <p>Now for <hi>Ceremony</hi> and <hi>Order,</hi> the endleſs Diſpute in this Iſland. How ſhall we <hi>prove</hi> this? what <hi>Rule</hi> have we for theſe? Here, as no where elſe, do I look that my authority ſhould be acoepted: How can it, when the Churches is denied? a very demonſtration from ſo private a perſon ſhall not paſs.</p>
            <p>Yet I deem theſe things cannot be baniſhed out of the Church: My reaſon is, all <hi>Beauty</hi> lies in <hi>Order,</hi> all <hi>Decency</hi> in <hi>Ceremony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With Order there is Beauty even in the Furrowes of the Field, and without it there is none in the Beds of a Garden, <hi>Irrational</hi> is the deſpoiling of Order, hence ſuch care taken, leaſt the Swine break into the Garden.</p>
            <p>God by the very Creation is a <hi>God of Order,</hi> Gen. i. <hi>And behold all was very good; altogether</hi> as well as <hi>each</hi> particular. Beſides his Title of <hi>Lord of Hosts</hi> ſhews as much: Every one that knows what belongs to an <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> knows without <hi>Order</hi> 'tis nothing.</p>
            <p>Yea and <hi>Nature</hi> her ſelf is not without her <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> the Leaves of the Trees, and the Flowers of the Field; <hi>Solomon</hi> in all his <hi>Ceremony</hi> could not out-ſtrip them: and ſo <hi>decent</hi> are theſe, that without them the Trees look <hi>bald,</hi> and the Earth withers into <hi>deſert.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So in <hi>Animals,</hi> the Houſe-Cock hath his <hi>Spur</hi> and <hi>Creſt,</hi> the Enſigns of Chivalry, the reſt of the Birds have their <hi>Habits</hi> and <hi>Liveries,</hi> the Turkies neck is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94901:16"/>
               <hi>fac'd</hi> with Scarlet, and the Lapwing hath his <hi>Cap of Maintenance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet nearer, The <hi>hair</hi> of our Face and <hi>Beard</hi> is but a <hi>Ceremony, viz.</hi> a mark of diſtinction and decency: and theſe inſtances that I have given, are ſo much to the purpoſe, that 'tis known they have the <hi>Fate</hi> of <hi>Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,</hi> to wit, to be thought <hi>ſuperfluous,</hi> as the Goats Beard, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet given no queſtion by the wiſe Creator for <hi>uſe</hi> and ornament; but we that perceive not the Divine Reaſon herein, think them idle luxuriant <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creſcencies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We know what our Saviour hath expreſs'd againſt <hi>Traditions,</hi> and we do more then partly believe him: He doth at no hand condemn any <hi>Tradition</hi> or <hi>Rite</hi> of the Elders <hi>directly;</hi> mark that, but ſuch only as mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly thwart the Word of God; ſuch are the <hi>unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> neglect of maintenance of our needy Parents upon a religious pretence of <hi>Corban,</hi> S. <hi>Mark</hi> vii.11. As for <hi>waſhing of the hands</hi> he condemneth it, but not <hi>direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> as if unlawful in it ſelf, becauſe no where com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, (as S. <hi>Chryſostome</hi> uncautelouſly lets fall) but <hi>indirectly,</hi> i.e. in ſuch a perſon whoſe <hi>ſcrupulous Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite</hi> could make great conſcience for the leſs, and none of the greater. Thus elſewhere he condemneth the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> yea pronounceth <hi>woe</hi> againſt them in ſeveral caſes, <hi>Matth.</hi> xxiii. Firſt, <hi>Woe to you Scribes, Phariſees, Hypocrites, for you compaſs Sea and Land</hi> to make a Proſelyte: A woe (and yet no fault in the World) All Religion that is good, or believes it ſelf to be good will do ſo. But what followes? <hi>You make him a child of Hell twofold more then your ſelves.</hi> Again, <hi>Wo to you Scribes, Phariſees, Hypocrites, becauſe you garniſh the Tombs of the Prophets, and ſay, If we had been in the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94901:16"/>dayes of our Fathers,</hi> &amp;c. No faults again, none I hope in that repentant expreſſion, <hi>If we,</hi> &amp;c. But chiefly that of <hi>tithing Mint and Cummin,</hi> which our Saviour ſaith they ought to have obſerved, and yet <hi>woe to the</hi> Scribes for ſuch tithing, whilſt they <hi>omit the great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Law,</hi> S. <hi>Matth.</hi> xxiii.23.</p>
            <p>And if I much miſtake not, our Saviour puts this difference and <hi>distinction</hi> himſelf, the <hi>phraſe</hi> of the Text being clearly <hi>altered</hi> in one from what it was in the other. In the matter of <hi>Corban</hi> our Saviour charges them home with <hi>making void Gods Law</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, This is ſinful and impudent; but in the Waſhing it is onely <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they are taxed for <hi>lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſide the Law</hi> of God, the Law of greater matters, S. <hi>Mark</hi> vii.8.</p>
            <p>But doth our Saviour deny any where, That he which maketh conſcience of the <hi>great</hi> matters of the Law, may be (if he will) punctual in the <hi>leſs.</hi> If the Phariſees heart ſhould be clean waſh'd, would the waſhing of his hands defile him? Let any man judge what our Saviour did, and all his Diſciples at the Marriage of <hi>Cana</hi> in <hi>Galilee,</hi> where there were <hi>ſix Water-pots</hi> ſet for this Ceremony, yea and other times alſo. As an innocent Ceremony doth not <hi>ſanctifie</hi> a man, ſo neither doth it <hi>defile</hi> him. Let us take heed of hypocriſie, and ſecure the greater matters, and the leſs are free for us: <hi>To the clean all things are clean,</hi> Tit. i.13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ceremonies</hi> may be ſuperciliouſly cenſur'd (poor things) but as the <hi>Herald</hi> ſays, In civil matters there can be no <hi>State or Majesty,</hi> ſo in Religion there can be no Devotion, no <hi>ſolemnity</hi> without them.</p>
            <p>All wiſe men know, that Religion is not a <hi>meer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,</hi> nothing outward: For how then ſhall our Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94901:17"/>be edified? How ſhall our Religion be <hi>profeſſed?</hi> How <hi>ſolemnly</hi> profeſſed? If there be in Religion a <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity,</hi> there muſt be ſome ſuch thing as a becoming Ceremony. The unhappy <hi>Covenant</hi> could not be the <hi>ſolemn</hi> League and Covenant, without the aſſumption of an outward Ceremony, <hi>lifting up of the hand to ſwear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I appeal to any man that hath a heart humbly to ſerve God, whether when he compoſeth himſelf to devout <hi>powring out</hi> of his ſoul to God, he can forbear the <hi>natural expreſſion</hi> of his eye and hand with heart. <hi>Let us lift up our hearts and hands to God in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens,</hi> Lam. iii.41. I ask whether the <hi>Publican</hi> could for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear in his holy indignation againſt his enemy (himſelf) to <hi>ſmite his breaſt.</hi> There is a <hi>natural ſpring</hi> in our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, that moves our hands, and eyes, and knees accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our inward affection. And as I remember, pious <hi>Anatomists</hi> give the reaſon why Nature made our eyes with ſuch <hi>Muſcles,</hi> and our knees with ſuch a <hi>Flexure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>God muſt be worſhipped in Spirit and Truth,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he may not be worſhipped by <hi>Ceremony</hi> only: But muſt he therefore be worſhipped without <hi>any?</hi> It is enough for me that our bleſſed Saviour, who beſt knew his own meaning uſed them, when in the <hi>ſolemn</hi> time of his laſt Devotion, he <hi>ador'd on his</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">S. Matth. xxvi.39.</note> face, yea and on the <hi>Croſs</hi> it ſelf, when he delivered up his torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſpirit to the Father, the Text ſaith, He<note n="*" place="margin">S. John xix.30.</note> 
               <hi>Bowed his head, and gave up the Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They that will ſay a Ceremony is juſt <hi>nothing,</hi> ſhould be ask'd, how they would take it, if any one ſhould <hi>ſpit</hi> in their faces, 'tis but the <hi>Ceremony</hi> of DeFiance. Or if Chriſts Diſciples ſhould <hi>ſhake off the duſt of their feet</hi> for a teſtimony againſt them, <hi>Matth.</hi> x.14.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:94901:17"/>
            <p>I am ſure our Saviour expects ſuch teſtimonies from us. See what he ſaith to his friend <hi>Simon,</hi> when the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonious Woman came in that wiped his feet; <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, I have ſomething to ſay to thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Luke vii.44.</note> He accuſes him of the defect of a <hi>triple Ceremony,</hi> and then brings in the Woman for a ſairer example; <hi>Thou gave me no water to waſh my feet, this Woman hath waſhed me with her tears,</hi> thou gaveſt me <hi>no kiſs,</hi> this Woman hath not ceaſed to <hi>kiſs my feet;</hi> my <hi>head with oyl</hi> thou didſt not anoint, this Woman hath <hi>anointed my feet with oyntment:</hi> And what is the concluſion? <hi>He loved little, and ſhe loved much.</hi> So true is it, there is no <hi>devotion</hi> without them.</p>
            <p>Our Adverſaries therefore would have done ill to have lived in the dayes of Chriſts fleſh, who might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps have been contented to have cried <hi>Hoſanna,</hi> but they would have ſcarce made one at gathering of <hi>bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> to ſtrew Chriſts way; they would hardly have laid their <hi>Carpets</hi> and <hi>Garments</hi> in his Road; while his Diſciples laid all under the feet of his very <hi>Beaſt,</hi> S. <hi>Matth.</hi> xxi.8.</p>
            <p>I know theſe practiſes are liable to exception. The holy Womans ointment <hi>Judas</hi> put in <hi>ad quid praeditio haec? Had not it been better ſold and given to the poor?</hi> And yet our Saviour defended that Woman. So to lay my Garments under an Aſſes feet, What ſenſe is for that? Yet our Saviour <hi>accepted</hi> this; and <hi>God</hi> give us grace to do thoſe things that our Saviour will <hi>accept.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now to the Rule: What is the <hi>Rule</hi> of theſe things? <hi>R.</hi> Affection, Charity. A high eſteem is the Fountain and Rule of theſe expreſſions: You do not hear me ſay a <hi>distinct Text</hi> of holy Scripture, that is for the <hi>greater matters</hi> of the Law: There was no <hi>expreſs Scripture</hi> for tithing of the Mint.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:94901:18"/>
            <p>The Apoſtle is diſcourſing of theſe things, 'tis good to ask him, What is the <hi>Rule</hi> of Ceremonies; The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle anſwers, <hi>Light of Nature,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> xi.14. What is the <hi>Rule</hi> (again) the ſame Apoſtle anſwers, <hi>Cuſtome</hi> the <hi>decent, rational cuſtome</hi> of the Church of God, <hi>ver.</hi> 16. Nay, but what is the <hi>Rule?</hi> The Apoſtle anſwers, (We know not how he will pleaſe you) Tradition Apoſtolick, <hi>ver.</hi> 2. Which places if again conſulted, you ſhall find that he ſpeaks of ſuch <hi>Natural Light,</hi> as it is <hi>ſhame</hi> not to obey: Such <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> which have enough in them to ſilence the <hi>Contentious,</hi> and ſuch <hi>Traditions</hi> as he praiſes them for obſerving, and exhorts them to <hi>hold faſt,</hi> and ſo I am upon my Text this third time, <hi>Prove all things, hold faſt that which is good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> abroad, with open face acknowledge, that <hi>much</hi> is to be attributed to the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> of the Church, that it is no <hi>Derogation</hi> to the <hi>Perfection of Scriptures</hi> imployed in the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of <hi>Greater</hi> Articles to leave the <hi>leſs</hi> to the Publique Wiſedome of the Church: but 'tis not the Intereſt of ours at home, that theſe things ſhould be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of. Yet let <hi>Chamiers</hi> 9th Book <hi>de Canone</hi> be conſulted, particularly <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 20. where he ſaith, <hi>Et ſanè illum oportet eſſe oris impudentiſſimi qui eam (Traditionem, Conſuetudinem Eccleſiae) contemnat. Nos verò illum parum abest quin ſacrilegum appellemus, &amp; quidem non tantum in Rebus levioribus</hi> (the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies) &amp;c. <hi>ſed</hi> &amp; <hi>grauioribus,</hi> &amp;c. Et ix. <hi>cap.</hi> xviii. <hi>ſect.</hi> 52. <hi>Reſp. per obſervantias nulla dogmata intelligi, ſed duntaxat varios ritus, quorum exempla quaedam ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nectit</hi> (ſpeaking of <hi>Origen</hi>) <hi>Genu flexionem, converſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ad Orientem, Ritus ſumendae Euchariſtiae,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui illa omnia Catholici</hi> (the Proteſtants) <hi>libere per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittunt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:94901:18"/>Traditioni.</hi> But once more (for I appeal to the whole Book) he hath theſe words: <hi>Hinc autem non ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur Scripturas eſſe imperfectas, niſi prius demonſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur dogmata Fidei ab Apostolis inſtituta eſſe quae omninò ſcripta non ſunt,</hi> ix.20, 32. For as to the <hi>Rites,</hi> he ſaies, It is not denied, <hi>quandam ab Apostolis potuiſſe constitui, quae quia non eſſent de eſſentia &amp; naturafidei, minùs cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravint ſcriptis referre,</hi> ix.19, 20. Pray let it be ponder'd.</p>
            <p>The ſame reaſon give we. <hi>Scripture</hi> is not their <hi>Rule,</hi> becauſe it is <hi>above</hi> them. Secondly, Becauſe they are of a <hi>mutable</hi> condition, where the firſt conſtituent Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the practiſe proves to be ſuch; otherwiſe not. There are ſome <hi>Traditions</hi> immutable, which 'tis not in the power of the Church to change, as the inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lords Day fixed on the firſt day of the Week, and yet they bely <hi>Calvin</hi> if he would not have changed it to <hi>Thurſday;</hi> but that Reaſon of our <hi>Lords Reſurrection</hi> hath determined it to that day of the Week, as the <hi>Sabbath</hi> by another was determined to the Jew.</p>
            <p>Here it is to be noted, when we ſay Cuſtome or Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, we do not mean an <hi>Arbitrary</hi> uſage of the Church, as the Gentry put on their Garments, and the Ladies their <hi>Fancies,</hi> meerly for <hi>variety,</hi> but there is diſcernible with it ſomething more of moment, either the <hi>Light of Nature,</hi> as in all Humble Poſtures, Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Feſtivals, many times <hi>Gods and Christs own Wiſdome and Spirit,</hi> in <hi>all</hi> of them <hi>Reaſon</hi> ſufficient to conſtitute them.</p>
            <p>For why the Apoſtles <hi>Love-Feaſt?</hi> Why the <hi>Veil?</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Jude xii. 1 Cor. xi.10. 2 Cor. xiii.13.</note> Why the <hi>Holy Kiſs?</hi> Why the <hi>Love-Feaſt?</hi> becauſe it was <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Love:</hi> the <hi>Reaſon</hi> is in the <hi>Name.</hi> Why the <hi>Kiſs?</hi> the <hi>Reaſon</hi> is in the appellation a <hi>Holy Kiſs,</hi> a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:94901:19"/>
               <hi>Kiſs of Charity?</hi> Why the <hi>Vail?</hi> becauſe of <hi>Modesty</hi> and <hi>Reſervedneſs</hi> in the Virgin in the preſence of <hi>God</hi> and his holy <hi>Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not adde thereto,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. xi.</note> 
               <hi>nor diminiſh therefrom,</hi> eſtabliſheth <hi>Gods</hi> authority, but it doth not <hi>overthrow</hi> his Churches. <hi>Moſes</hi> his Chair and the <hi>Sanedrim</hi> were put up by God to make <hi>Canons</hi> of Church and State in points not decidible by the <hi>Text.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Church of God always knew it her Innocent Right to ordain a <hi>Ceremony</hi> on a juſt Reaſon, before <hi>Moſes</hi> was born, <hi>Gen.</hi> xxxii.32. witneſs the <hi>abstaining</hi> from the <hi>ſinew</hi> in memory of <hi>Jacobs wrestling:</hi> ſo do the Jews ever ſince obſerve <hi>ſolemn Fasts</hi> for <hi>Miriams</hi> Leproſie, <hi>Moſes</hi> his <hi>breaking of the Tables,</hi> and the <hi>Death of the ſons of Aaron,</hi> as the learned <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> hath noted them and more for us in his Ages of the World.</p>
            <p>Many that are uſed to this day come from <hi>Gods</hi> own <hi>wiſdome</hi> under the <hi>Law-Diſpenſation,</hi> and therefore <hi>adopted</hi> by the Church under the Goſpel; the Spirit of Chriſt ſo thought it good, who is thereby throughly witneſſed to the Jew to be their <hi>Meſſias,</hi> promiſed by the God of their Fathers, in <hi>this,</hi> that (bating the meer <hi>ſhadows</hi> and ſervile work, in whoſe room he hath put <hi>ſubſtantial</hi> and more glorious ſervices) in founding his Church he hath <hi>retained</hi> all that was <hi>fit,</hi> and <hi>ſolemn,</hi> and <hi>decent,</hi> ſuch as are the <hi>distinction</hi> of the Courts of the Lords Houſe, the <hi>Orders</hi> of Prieſt and Levite, their hours of Prayer, their attendances <hi>by night</hi> in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>ſecubations</hi> in times of Humiliation, the <hi>Baptiſm</hi> of the Infant about the eighth day, the <hi>giving of the Name</hi> at Baptiſm, and the <hi>Godfathers</hi> (at they uſed at Circumciſion) the <hi>ſecluſion</hi> of the Woman after <hi>Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing</hi> for a <hi>Moneths</hi> ſpace, the <hi>Reading the Law</hi> in their Synagogues, their <hi>ſinging,</hi> the Hebrew <hi>Amen,</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:94901:19"/>and <hi>Alleluja,</hi> the <hi>Dominical</hi> day for the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> nay our very <hi>Sacraments</hi> themſelves advanced from the Jews who had their <hi>Baptiſm and Cup Eucharistical,</hi> and many others in which God, God I ſay is viſibly evident.</p>
            <p>I ſhould <hi>ſurfet</hi> you, if I ſhould lead you as I thought to have done through every particular; but at preſent it cannot be.</p>
            <p>Only thus far have I attempted to bring all good Chriſtians to <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi> Let no man do me that wrong paſt repair, to think that I have in any of this an <hi>evil eye</hi> toward the holy <hi>Scripture;</hi> whatſoever is ſaid I wiſh un-ſaid, that is not <hi>proved</hi> thereby.</p>
            <p>If for matters of <hi>Faith</hi> and practical <hi>conſcience</hi> the holy <hi>Scriptures</hi> ſuppoſe the <hi>Creed</hi> and <hi>Light of Nature,</hi> it cannot <hi>exclude</hi> them. If for matters of <hi>Ceremony</hi> the Scripture <hi>undertaketh</hi> not, but commendeth to us other ſubordinate <hi>authority,</hi> let thoſe places be <hi>expunged,</hi> or elſe we <hi>dare</hi> not ſay but what we have ſaid. If we be judged by <hi>Scriptures,</hi> let us be judged by <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and he that maketh conſcience of <hi>one</hi> clauſe, muſt make conſcience of <hi>all</hi> uniformly, or elſe he had better never ſeen it. Would men but conſider this.</p>
            <p>That the holy Scripture is the <hi>Rule,</hi> I have not inſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on, becauſe I took it for granted, and I ſhould have been tedious in aſſerting what every body knows. It is <hi>a Rule,</hi> and <hi>ſuch a Rule,</hi> that he that loves his ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt diligently attend it: ſee how many <hi>Precepts</hi> are in it. (Think not of x or xx, but of x times xx) And as <hi>many</hi> as there are, I never counted my ſelf to underſtand any thing, till I perfectly believed that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of them were my <hi>Rule</hi> in order to ſalvation: ſo that men of unwary converſations (ſuch as I am) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not read them without a ſigh and ſhaking of the head,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:94901:20"/>as S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> uſes to ſay, <hi>Yerret me,</hi> this and that Precept <hi>frights me,</hi> when I know how far I come ſhort.</p>
            <p>All that I have laboured for is, that the Scripture may not be <hi>wrested,</hi> that we may not <hi>loſe</hi> the fruit of it by <hi>abuſing</hi> it. Hereby will I, nill I, owning it to be a <hi>Rule,</hi> if it be but in this, that it is liable to be <hi>wrested.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let no man ſtrange that Scripture may be <hi>abuſed,</hi> (as profane and audacious as the Practiſe is, though I fear not commonly thought ſo) even by thoſe that ſeem to cry it up. How do we take it, when ſome cry up <hi>Liberty</hi> to bring in <hi>Confuſion?</hi> Do they not <hi>abuſe</hi> Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thereby? The <hi>ſeditious</hi> Party do ſo. What think you of thoſe that magnifie <hi>grace</hi> in flat oppoſition to <hi>all duty?</hi> Do they not <hi>abuſe</hi> it? the <hi>Autinomian</hi> does ſo. Nay, if one ſhall cry up <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> himſelf (can <hi>Chriſt</hi> be extolled too much? yea, but if he ſhould be ſet up) in <hi>oppoſition</hi> to his Father, I have ſeen a <hi>Curſed Paper</hi> do ſo. Nothing is done right, but what is <hi>ſtated</hi> according to its due limits of explication. This is the ſourſe of all our miſery.</p>
            <p>And now this objection is out of the way, how ſhall I beſpeak you to return to the <hi>unity</hi> of that Church, to which, if you had once <hi>proved</hi> all things by <hi>Scripture Rules,</hi> you muſt at laſt retire: the worſt that you can gain is the character of an <hi>understanding</hi> and <hi>peaceable</hi> perſon, a <hi>wiſe</hi> man, and a <hi>meek</hi> one. Why muſt a <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony</hi> fright you? What deformed Multiplying-Glaſs do you ſee that in, which of it ſelf is <hi>rational, innocent,</hi> and <hi>ſolemn?</hi> Do we place the <hi>ſubstance</hi> of Religion in them? Nay, we ſay indeed there is no <hi>outward</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion without them, no <hi>real</hi> body but what will caſt its <hi>ſhadow.</hi> Which of us would not have cenſur'd <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> of <hi>ſuperstition</hi> to have wiped Chriſts <hi>feet</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:94901:20"/>with her <hi>hair,</hi> and have pitied the ignorance of thoſe men that threw their <hi>Garments</hi> under our Saviours <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> feet? How many counted our Saviour himſelf a <hi>breaker of the Sabbath</hi> (becauſe they conſulted not right reaſon) and how many a <hi>Blaſphemer</hi> (becauſe they knew not his <hi>authority</hi>) Our Lord was not <hi>ſtanch</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for thoſe that called him <hi>wine-bibber,</hi> and the holy Baptiſt for his <hi>fasting</hi> and prayer had a <hi>Devil.</hi> Have we no need of <hi>proving</hi> all things, and take in all the <hi>lights</hi> and <hi>helps</hi> that God vouchſafes us? Let not <hi>Reaſon, Creed, Scripture, Chriſt, all</hi> be <hi>against</hi> us, for in the end they will be <hi>too hard</hi> for us.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
